<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.6">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-08-07T19:47:25+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">xiq</title><entry><title type="html">Language And Inner Scuba Diving</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/06/25/language-and-inner-scuba-diving.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Language And Inner Scuba Diving" /><published>2019-06-25T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-06-25T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/06/25/language-and-inner-scuba-diving</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/06/25/language-and-inner-scuba-diving.html">&lt;p&gt;What if by learning languages, you could be exploring the depths of the psyche as a side-effect?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been learning mandarin for a few months and my brain has been PULSING because of all the slight flavours of words and sounds, and the nuances in phrases for everyday tasks and objects. I haven’t even gotten very deep into abstract concepts, but I can see it’s a totally separate space. Feels like exploring a familiar place in a parallel dimension, with diffent textures and colors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Romantically, I like to think of languagesas products of the stories and recurring common experiences of their speakers throughout the ages. Speaking and thinking in several languages as window into fundamental human-ness. Not because individual words themselves shine light on archetypes (although there may be some particularly tidy showcases of this that I’m missing), but because of the whole of a language offering insight into the experience of its speakers, integrating into one’s own mind some of the perspective and identity of a people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://fractalsidequests.files.wordpress.com/2019/06/wechat-image_20190625164915-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;Chinese ethnolinguistic groups&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Borrowing Wittgenstein’s term, we can look at languages as collections of “language games” and by collecting, identifying, and integrating the common and idiosyncratic rulesets present in different contexts, we may construct better models of the mind. Many of these games may be constringent on the environment they originated in; some of them will be very similar, and those might be distilled to improve one’s understanding of human condition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, given language originates for communication between individuals, might it merely provide superficial insights into the inner landscape? Probably not. Our inner fauna of archetypes is likely what evolved to produce useful behaviours from inside, and certainly has a big role in developing these protocols by which we coordinate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://fractalsidequests.files.wordpress.com/2019/06/th.jpg =411x308&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Man’s task&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Man’s task is…to become conscious of the contents that press upward from the unconscious. Neither should he persist in his unconsciousness nor remain identical with the unconscious elements of his being, thus evading his destiny, which is to create more and more consciousness. As far as we can discern, the sole purpose of human existence is to kindle a light in the darkness of mere being.” (Memories, Dreams, Reflections, Carl Jung)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world outside is vast and full of complexity and color and fun, but so is the one within. The inner space is mapped a lot less than the outside one. Presumably because the most useful part of it is what’s common across people, the collective unconscious. The CU is the rocky landscape on which the sediments and seeds of the individual unconscious and the conscious selves are set and grow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://fractalsidequests.files.wordpress.com/2019/06/flags-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;Princess Wencheng Memorial site, Yushu, Qinghai, Tibetan Plateau&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People explore their interior by meditating, thinking, having conversations, by taking drugs, and having deep relationships, but I’d never considered you could get deep insight into the collective unconscious by learning languages and using them to understand things that aren’t explicit or even explainable in any single one, commonalities only evident from several points at once. That’s beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Disclaimer: I found this book called&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oxfordscholarship.com/view/10.1093/acprof:oso/9780195311129.001.0001/acprof-9780195311129&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Words and the Mind, How Words Capture Human Experience”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;that I should probably have read before writing about this, but since I haven’t posted in a while (exam season + backpacking in Tibet) I just decided to publish and get rid of these paragraphs that had been staring at me for way too long.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">What if by learning languages, you could be exploring the depths of the psyche as a side-effect?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Mind And Other Incipient Ecologies</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/05/21/the-mind-and-other-incipient-ecologies.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Mind And Other Incipient Ecologies" /><published>2019-05-21T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-05-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/05/21/the-mind-and-other-incipient-ecologies</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/05/21/the-mind-and-other-incipient-ecologies.html">&lt;p&gt;When I was in high-school I had a ton of anxiety and was uncertain about most things, so I did like ~&lt;em&gt;muhboi&lt;/em&gt;~ Descartes and stripped my beliefs to the bare “I think therefore I am” and went from there, maybe I’d finally be sure about some things. I don’t recall the whole process but in retrospect I felt very postmodern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/dfw.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Later I read some Camus followed by a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GopJ1x7vK2Q&quot;&gt;David Foster Wallace interview&lt;/a&gt; and suddenly I understood that although nothing means anything intrinsically, we’re all better off being nice and finding meaning in each other.&lt;br /&gt;
Lately, I mostly think in interacting systems, emergent properties (like the survival of the fittest [or more accurately the dying of the unfit]), and try to formalize things/compress knowledge.&lt;br /&gt;
It feels good, and actually feels like I understand a lot more than before, even despite mistrusting the validity of my thought more often. I’m struggling to find a balance between poetry and rigor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On one hand, I’m trying to better trust my intuitions. On the other, these are just learned heuristics with varying degrees of certainty. Knowing well that it’s all too easy to lower standards in order to make a puzzle piece fit neatly, (the most vivid example being how easy it is to come up with a plausible &lt;em&gt;evopsych&lt;/em&gt; argument) I start questioning how one might calibrate between nonsense and likely good open minded hypotheses about the nature of things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.history.com/.image/ar_16:9%2Cc_fill%2Ccs_srgb%2Cfl_progressive%2Cg_faces:center%2Cq_auto:good%2Cw_768/MTU3ODc5MDg3MjQwMzI0NDI1/making-flints.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;What I invariably think about when &lt;em&gt;evopsych&lt;/em&gt; comes up&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My current world model is centered around a hard core of science and mathematics surrounded by a gooey crown of theories and intuition (kind of like personalities in &lt;a href=&quot;https://meltingasphalt.com/prickles-and-goo/&quot;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt;). Inside that hard core, is (by epistemological necessity) yet another ball of goo (that might one day envelop everything else). This more or less represents the axioms of mathematics, the uncertainty surrounding the incompatibility between physical theories, and the incomprehensible recursion of human condition. The ungrounded central beliefs on which our collective understanding of the world rests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://fractalsidequests.files.wordpress.com/2019/05/goo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;Primordial goo! Brimming with possibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t like it, but I need this outer goo for the kind of broad, general insight I’m after. The type of scientific rigor that would make my points unquestionable is intractable in useful time. I’m not trying to solve life and the universe, but I am definitely after a rough pirate’s map of it, or at least a somewhat magnetized compass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To keep scouting ahead, we need to prioritize the most viscous goo available (the ideas most likely to be factual). &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lindy_effect&quot;&gt;Lindy&lt;/a&gt; things, like tradition, old sayings, and ancient wisdom might be forms of goo (in that they’re not explicitly grounded in empiric evidence) but they are some of the thickest goo available, because they’ve been empirically tested implicitly by time, and can serve as proxy “intellectual bedrock” provided you can weed out the ones that have recently been rendered invalid by the exponentially frequent tectonic shifts of the information age. That the fast changing nature of the present renders much of the value of popular sayings and religious wisdom useless is a great topic on its own and one that isn’t as straightforward as it might seem, discrediting valuable spiritual teachings along with the chaff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/wheat.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of chaff, I’ve been separating a lot of wheat from it for the past few years and I’m not even close to being close to being done(and again, wonder if it’s not just turtles of abstraction all the way down), but the nomadic ideas in my brain are starting to settle the land and farm a bit, at least until the next mindquake. Maybe it’s time to develop some primitive mental institutions to keep anarchy at bay. No courts, or banks, or anything too fancy, it’s not quite a city yet. Some rituals, a bit of accounting, and a regular council in the form of a journal entry should be enough for now.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">When I was in high-school I had a ton of anxiety and was uncertain about most things, so I did like ~muhboi~ Descartes and stripped my beliefs to the bare “I think therefore I am” and went from there, maybe I’d finally be sure about some things. I don’t recall the whole process but in retrospect I felt very postmodern.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dream Supplies</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/05/08/dream-supplies.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dream Supplies" /><published>2019-05-08T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-05-08T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/05/08/dream-supplies</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/05/08/dream-supplies.html">&lt;p&gt;Been on the road a lot since the semester started in Beijing. I’ve seen the ancient capital of Xi’an, the millennarian Buddhist caves of Datong, and strolled the former concession metropolis of Tianjin, all as weekend trips. Right now I’m in the middle of the most ambitious outing yet: a two-week long shitty triangle across central China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/chinacloseup.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our not-quite-triangular itinerary through east/central China&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strolling through Mao’s native province of Hunan, I can’t help but wonder. This is all pretty cool, and I got to see some crazy mountains and temples, but when my favorite parts of it all were spending the night in a tent inside an abandoned house, and looking at a bunch of monkeys for way too much time, what does that tell me about my (relatively) expensive tour?&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/wildcamping.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wild camping taught me there’s always a plan B when the sky is your roof&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Planned tourist trips are fine. Even necessary if I want to cover as much ground as I’m able in the 4 months I have in the middle kingdom; but I think they might be fundamentally different things from open-ended travelling periods. I mean, there’s definitely a spectrum. Watching a movie at the cinema isn’t the same as watching it on netflix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/monkeymom.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mother and son in Uncanny Valley&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This feeling tells me what I’m probably looking for right now is a certain”on your own”-ness, the feeling of dealing with the unexpected myself, and of being responsible for whatever happens to me to a degree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/karst.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Karst peaks are the stuff of dreams&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In defense of sight-seeing, I don’t think it’s a waste of time. There are things you do keep after the pleasurable fact. I like to think of it as gathering “dream material”. Memories of places you inhabit stick with you more or less permanently, stored in the boundless unconscious. There they become available for your imagination to draw from and to melt into the countless other things you’ve seen, manifesting themselves in your dreams, making them and you richer and deeper. Like soul-fertilizer.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Been on the road a lot since the semester started in Beijing. I’ve seen the ancient capital of Xi’an, the millennarian Buddhist caves of Datong, and strolled the former concession metropolis of Tianjin, all as weekend trips. Right now I’m in the middle of the most ambitious outing yet: a two-week long shitty triangle across central China.</summary></entry></feed>