<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.6">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-08-05T23:07:37+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><entry><title type="html">The Mind And Other Incipient Ecologies</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/05/08/the-mind-and-other-incipient-ecologies.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Mind And Other Incipient Ecologies" /><published>2019-05-08T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-05-08T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/05/08/the-mind-and-other-incipient-ecologies</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/05/08/the-mind-and-other-incipient-ecologies.html">&lt;p&gt;When I was in high-school I had a ton of anxiety and was uncertain about most things, so I did like ~&lt;em&gt;muhboi&lt;/em&gt;~ Descartes and stripped my beliefs to the bare “I think therefore I am” and went from there, maybe I’d finally be sure about some things. I don’t recall the whole process but in retrospect I felt very postmodern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/dfw.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Later I read some Camus followed by a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GopJ1x7vK2Q&quot;&gt;David Foster Wallace interview&lt;/a&gt; and suddenly I understood that although nothing means anything intrinsically, we’re all better off being nice and finding meaning in each other.&lt;br /&gt;
Lately, I mostly think in interacting systems, emergent properties (like the survival of the fittest [or more accurately the dying of the unfit]), and try to formalize things/compress knowledge.&lt;br /&gt;
It feels good, and actually feels like I understand a lot more than before, even despite mistrusting the validity of my thought more often. I’m struggling to find a balance between poetry and rigor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On one hand, I’m trying to better trust my intuitions. On the other, these are just learned heuristics with varying degrees of certainty. Knowing well that it’s all too easy to lower standards in order to make a puzzle piece fit neatly, (the most vivid example being how easy it is to come up with a plausible &lt;em&gt;evopsych&lt;/em&gt; argument) I start questioning how one might calibrate between nonsense and likely good open minded hypotheses about the nature of things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.history.com/.image/ar_16:9%2Cc_fill%2Ccs_srgb%2Cfl_progressive%2Cg_faces:center%2Cq_auto:good%2Cw_768/MTU3ODc5MDg3MjQwMzI0NDI1/making-flints.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;What I invariably think about when &lt;em&gt;evopsych&lt;/em&gt; comes up&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My current world model is centered around a hard core of science and mathematics surrounded by a gooey crown of theories and intuition (kind of like personalities in &lt;a href=&quot;https://meltingasphalt.com/prickles-and-goo/&quot;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt;). Inside that hard core, is (by epistemological necessity) yet another ball of goo (that might one day envelop everything else). This more or less represents the axioms of mathematics, the uncertainty surrounding the incompatibility between physical theories, and the incomprehensible recursion of human condition. The ungrounded central beliefs on which our collective understanding of the world rests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://fractalsidequests.files.wordpress.com/2019/05/goo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;Primordial goo! Brimming with possibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t like it, but I need this outer goo for the kind of broad, general insight I’m after. The type of scientific rigor that would make my points unquestionable is intractable in useful time. I’m not trying to solve life and the universe, but I am definitely after a rough pirate’s map of it, or at least a somewhat magnetized compass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To keep scouting ahead, we need to prioritize the most viscous goo available (the ideas most likely to be factual). &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lindy_effect&quot;&gt;Lindy&lt;/a&gt; things, like tradition, old sayings, and ancient wisdom might be forms of goo (in that they’re not explicitly grounded in empiric evidence) but they are some of the thickest goo available, because they’ve been empirically tested implicitly by time, and can serve as proxy “intellectual bedrock” provided you can weed out the ones that have recently been rendered invalid by the exponentially frequent tectonic shifts of the information age. That the fast changing nature of the present renders much of the value of popular sayings and religious wisdom useless is a great topic on its own and one that isn’t as straightforward as it might seem, discrediting valuable spiritual teachings along with the chaff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/wheat.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of chaff, I’ve been separating a lot of wheat from it for the past few years and I’m not even close to being close to being done(and again, wonder if it’s not just turtles of abstraction all the way down), but the nomadic ideas in my brain are starting to settle the land and farm a bit, at least until the next mindquake. Maybe it’s time to develop some primitive mental institutions to keep anarchy at bay. No courts, or banks, or anything too fancy, it’s not quite a city yet. Some rituals, a bit of accounting, and a regular council in the form of a journal entry should be enough for now.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">When I was in high-school I had a ton of anxiety and was uncertain about most things, so I did like ~muhboi~ Descartes and stripped my beliefs to the bare “I think therefore I am” and went from there, maybe I’d finally be sure about some things. I don’t recall the whole process but in retrospect I felt very postmodern.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dreamsupplies</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/05/08/dreamsupplies.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dreamsupplies" /><published>2019-05-08T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-05-08T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/05/08/dreamsupplies</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/05/08/dreamsupplies.html">&lt;p&gt;Been on the road a lot since the semester started in Beijing. I’ve seen the ancient capital of Xi’an, the millennarian Buddhist caves of Datong, and strolled the former concession metropolis of Tianjin, all as weekend trips. Right now I’m in the middle of the most ambitious outing yet: a two-week long shitty triangle across central China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/chinacloseup.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strolling through Mao’s native province of Hunan, I can’t help but wonder. This is all pretty cool, and I got to see some crazy mountains and temples, but when my favorite parts of it all were spending the night in a tent inside an abandoned house, and looking at a bunch of monkeys for way too much time, what does that tell me about my (relatively) expensive tour?&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/wildcamping.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Planned tourist trips are fine. Even necessary if I want to cover as much ground as I’m able in the 4 months I have in the middle kingdom; but I think they might be fundamentally different things from open-ended travelling periods. I mean, there’s definitely a spectrum. Watching a movie at the cinema isn’t the same as watching it on netflix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/monkeymom.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This feeling tells me what I’m probably looking for right now is a certain”on your own”-ness, the feeling of dealing with the unexpected myself, and of being responsible for whatever happens to me to a degree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/karst.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In defense of sight-seeing, I don’t think it’s a waste of time. There are things you do keep after the pleasurable fact. I like to think of it as gathering “dream material”. Memories of places you inhabit stick with you more or less permanently, stored in the boundless unconscious. There they become available for your imagination to draw from and to melt into the countless other things you’ve seen, manifesting themselves in your dreams, making them and you richer and deeper. Like soul-fertilizer.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Been on the road a lot since the semester started in Beijing. I’ve seen the ancient capital of Xi’an, the millennarian Buddhist caves of Datong, and strolled the former concession metropolis of Tianjin, all as weekend trips. Right now I’m in the middle of the most ambitious outing yet: a two-week long shitty triangle across central China.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dream Supplies</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/05/08/dream-supplies.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dream Supplies" /><published>2019-05-08T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-05-08T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/05/08/dream-supplies</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/05/08/dream-supplies.html">&lt;p&gt;Been on the road a lot since the semester started in Beijing. I’ve seen the ancient capital of Xi’an, the millennarian Buddhist caves of Datong, and strolled the former concession metropolis of Tianjin, all as weekend trips. Right now I’m in the middle of the most ambitious outing yet: a two-week long shitty triangle across central China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/chinacloseup.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strolling through Mao’s native province of Hunan, I can’t help but wonder. This is all pretty cool, and I got to see some crazy mountains and temples, but when my favorite parts of it all were spending the night in a tent inside an abandoned house, and looking at a bunch of monkeys for way too much time, what does that tell me about my (relatively) expensive tour?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;.&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/wildcamping.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;Planned tourist trips are fine. Even necessary if I want to cover as much ground as I’m able in the 4 months I have in the middle kingdom; but I think they might be fundamentally different things from open-ended travelling periods. I mean, there’s definitely a spectrum. Watching a movie at the cinema isn’t the same as watching it on netflix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/monkeymom.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This feeling tells me what I’m probably looking for right now is a certain”on your own”-ness, the feeling of dealing with the unexpected myself, and of being responsible for whatever happens to me to a degree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/karst.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In defense of sight-seeing, I don’t think it’s a waste of time. There are things you do keep after the pleasurable fact. I like to think of it as gathering “dream material”. Memories of places you inhabit stick with you more or less permanently, stored in the boundless unconscious. There they become available for your imagination to draw from and to melt into the countless other things you’ve seen, manifesting themselves in your dreams, making them and you richer and deeper. Like soul-fertilizer.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Been on the road a lot since the semester started in Beijing. I’ve seen the ancient capital of Xi’an, the millennarian Buddhist caves of Datong, and strolled the former concession metropolis of Tianjin, all as weekend trips. Right now I’m in the middle of the most ambitious outing yet: a two-week long shitty triangle across central China.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Apples</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/08/21/apples.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Apples" /><published>2018-08-21T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-08-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/08/21/apples</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/08/21/apples.html">&lt;p&gt;An apple is a sweet, edible fruit produced by an apple tree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apple trees are cultivated worldwide, and are the most widely grown species in
the genus Malus. The tree originated in Central Asia, where its wild ancestor,
Malus sieversii, is still found today. Apples have been grown for thousands of
years in Asia and Europe, and were brought to North America by European
colonists.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">An apple is a sweet, edible fruit produced by an apple tree.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bananas</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/08/20/bananas.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bananas" /><published>2018-08-20T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-08-20T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/08/20/bananas</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/08/20/bananas.html">&lt;p&gt;A banana is an edible fruit – botanically a berry – produced by several kinds
of large herbaceous flowering plants in the genus Musa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In some countries, bananas used for cooking may be called “plantains”,
distinguishing them from dessert bananas. The fruit is variable in size, color,
and firmness, but is usually elongated and curved, with soft flesh rich in
starch covered with a rind, which may be green, yellow, red, purple, or brown
when ripe.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">A banana is an edible fruit – botanically a berry – produced by several kinds of large herbaceous flowering plants in the genus Musa.</summary></entry></feed>